Russell Ward

Ph: 415 624 5895

611 18th St Oakland 94612

I am a web developer with a passion for harnessing the internet to communicate in compelling ways. I create online experiences that leave the user feeling better, provide interactions with technology to offer information and easy completion of tasks, and most importantly, inspire positive emotions.

My education in humanities, lifelong passion for the arts, and my multi-channel career in international advertising and running of my own web development shop all give me a creative breadth that I bring to focus on my front-end engineering. I have a flexibility of mind to learn new languages and patterns quickly. I like to work hard and bring passion to the work I do.

Skills

Javascript (and the Full Stack)

Front end ★ Node, React, CSS, HTML5, jQuery

Back end < comfortable with MongoDB, PHP, MySQL

Design 🗖 Photoshop, InDesign, Illustrator, PremierePro etc

Communication: I can listen and talk - I get fired up by the sharing of ideas and am able to communicate the essence and evolution of concepts and designs

Employment

SCHOOL LOOP - UX ENGINEER (2013-PRESENT)

As the primary front-end engineer, I am involved in all stages of developing and maintaining the front-end of the education portal used by over 200,000 users: students, parents, teachers and district administrators from about 350 districts around the US. I spend most of every day writing Javascript (jQuery when convenient), working with our backend engineers who use Java and Postgres. I'll adopt libraries as needed but often end up making a better one for our purposes. We develop with an agile approach and I regularly meet with UX designers, graphic designers, and our backend engineers. I run or am involved in user sessions to determine feature priorities and hone the flow for applications for users with a variety of comfort levels around technology.

Highlights include:

- building a WYSIWYG content management system enabling teachers and staff to easily create great websites, with a host of dynamic modules with easy styling options; groovy slideshows using CSS transitions and background videos; news; smooth calendars; assignments
- handling the mass of data (usually provided in JSON) to display in trend, grade and communications in easily accessible ways
- training in online accessibility which I use to help establish our products as industry leaders in compliance with ADA regulations
- being given the title "UX Good Times Engineer" because of the fun I generate on and offline

ZEN DEN WEBDESIGN - LEAD DEVELOPER (2010-2013)

In my senior position I regularly met with clients to help shape online solutions, from custom applications, completely new websites, and upgrades of old ones. I saw projects through from initial plans and specs to final testing and deployment. I guided junior members of the team and ensured that their work met the company's high standards. The job got my hands dirty with many languages and technologies, platforms and APIs: Wordpress, Magento, Python, Ruby, Actionscript.

Highlights include:

- V2consulting.com: custom solution that integrated 3 websites and syncing the databases with their CRM software for users to find and book MAC hardware training
- Jimmyjane.com: 2 years of projects including a stylish reviews application for the design-oriented sexual accessories company
- PaulinaCarcach.com: completely new ecommerce site featuring a design your own handbag application developed in Flash Actionscript

(See the demo here: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2KYXXdj8DOs)

— Putnam Toyota: a site for selling extended warranties online easily

SEVENPONDS - WEB DEVELOPER (2012)

I saw the development of this site for a great start-up through a successful launch:

- developed on an MVC pattern using the CodeIgniter framework
- created a custom CMS to allow easy admin control and an elegant user interface

A WORD IN YOUR EAR LTD - OWNER (2003-2013)

I built up A Word in your Ear Ltd for my work in web development, contract copywriting, design, and Search Engine Optimization. My stimulating variety of jobs has included:

- —Online marketing manager for crew2crew.com, social and professional networking for members of crew based industries (August 2008 September 2009)
- Creator and webmaster of grampianlife.co.uk, a site operated by me to serve the North East Scotland Grampian mountain region featuring an active forum funded by advertising from local businesses
- Designer, developer and webmaster of readingbus.co.uk, a non-profit which promotes literacy among a community of young learners a colorful and fun website
- Developer in partnership with a designer to build lit-tees.co.uk, a website that brings together a community of professional writers and publishers in the Tees Valley, North England
- other work included marketing copywriting for the Telephone Preferencing Service (UK), running SEO workshops, and developing email and online campaigns for small businesses

COPYWRITER - GREY INTERACTIVE - JOSHUA (LONDON) (1999-2003)

Teamed with a designer and a wide range of creative and technical personnel, my work included:

- effective websites, emails, rich-media, brochures, billboards, POS, CD ROMs, interactive TV ads, corporate videos
- developed cutting-edge creative concepts for a range of on-line, traditional, and integrated campaigns
- seeing work through all stages from initial concept to final delivery

Projects included:

- writing stories for an immersive environment with a 3d interactive hologram that was installed in 14 airports around Europe to give people a taste of "tomorrow's lifestyle today"
- Mars/M&M's Global Colour Vote, which attracted 700,000+ chocolate eaters to vote on my website
- an interactive TV ad for a 'Lilo and Stitch' & 'Flash' promotion
- innovative campaigns for Zurich Finance, Oracle, Sony, Barclays Stockbrokers, Unisys

Education

THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY

1990-94 Bachelor of Arts (1st Class Honors in English) 1995-98 PhD in English Literature (European Hellenism) - ABD

SYDNEY BOYS HIGH SCHOOL

1988 High School Certi cate 407/500 (top 9% in N.S.W.) Prefect, actor, debater, basketball player

Interests

Art — check out my iPad Paintings here: https://ausrussell.tumblr.com/Go — the ancient Chinese game - I'm ranked internationally as 4kyu Yoga — helps me code
Ancient Greek — regularly attend a reading group in SF
Sourdough bread — my starter named Claude is over 900days old

References

Mark Gross — CEO Schoolloop Ph: 650 220 6750

Tom Burns — CTO Schoolloop Ph: 415 845 3557

Chad Bell — CEO Zen Den Web Design

Ph: 415 938 6722